A Guide to Materials on Women
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection 1829-1915, ca. 1,000 items.
  The collection of John Henry Ingram, a biographer, editor and stalwart champion of Edgar Allan Poe. Ingram collected as much information on Poe as possible and the result is an unparallel collection of letters, manuscripts, daguerrotypes, and printed materials. Included as subjects or correspondents are: Sarah Helen Whitman, Susan Anna Power, Anna Blackwell, Sarah T. Bolton, Dr. Elizabeth Blackwell, Elizabeth Barrett Browning, Phoebe and Alice Cary, Lydia Marie Child, Mrs. Jane Clark, Rosa Durham, Elizabeth Frieze Ellet, Kate Field, Sarah Margaret Fuller, Godey's Lady Book, Sara Josepha Hale, E. Dora Houghton, Mary Louise Shew Houghton, The Ladies Wrath, Eliza Leslie, Sarah Ann Lewis, Mary Gove Nichols, Frances Sargent Osgood, Rose F. Peckham, Amelia Fitzgerlad Poe, Elisabeth Ellicott Poe, Elizabeth Arnold Hopkins Poe, Rosalie Poe, Virginia Clemm Poe, Sara Sigourney Rice, Nancy Richmond, Sarah Elmira Royster Shelton, Elizabeth Oakes Smith, Harriet Beecher Stowe, Susan Archer Talley Weiss, "A Woman the Cause!" and the Women's Literary Society of Baltimore. #38-135.
- Agnes Rothery Pratt Papers 1900-1940, 8 boxes
  Manuscripts, clippings, scrapbooks, correspondence, and miscellaneous printed material used by Mr. and Mrs. Pratt in his stories (pen name Henry Fearing) and her novels and travel books. Periodicals containing their works and reviews of them. #890, 2295, 3075, 3222, 3335
- Agnes Rothery Pratt Papers 1935-1942, 2 boxes.
  Correspondence, notes, and manuscripts for her Washington Roundabout and Family Album. #1366, 1388.
- Agnes Rothery Pratt Papers 1935-1950, 30 items.
  Manuscripts and pamphlets pertaining to Pratt's book Italian Roundabout; revised drafts of The Fitting Habitation; and a letter, October 14, 1935, from Agnes Repplier. #3674
- Josephine Preston Peabody Letter 1898, 1 item.
  Peabody writes to Professor Marsh, on December 8, 1898, asking him to correct in his copy of The Wayfarer a misprint in the Scripture quotation that prefaces the volume. She explains the appropriateness of the (unidentified) quotation, and claims that The envoy particularly speaks for her. #8184-a
- Quinby Family Papers 1759 (1800-1898) 1968, ca. 1300 items.
  The papers of the Teackle, Upshar and Quinby families of the Easter Shore of Maryland and Virginia. There is a substantial amount of correspondence generated by women, as well as, Elizabeth Upshar Teackles' commonplace books containing poetry. One item, December 2, 1778, is a copy of a letter from Nancy Cunningham of Philadelphia to Sally Teackle in which she describes her flight from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and informs Miss Teackle that her brother, Captain Severn Teackle, is alive and well in a British prison camp on Long Island. #2338
- Jane Porter and Anne Radcliffe 1794, 1840, 2 items.
  Two writers of Gothic novels. Ann Radcliffe, founder of the "explained supernatural" school of fiction, was the most popular novelist in English before Walter Scott. The contract for her most famous novel, Mysteries of Udolpho, is included in this collection. #1625
- Eliza Carter Randolph Letter 1796, 1 item.
  Eliza Carter Randolph writes to Ann F.B. Tucker on November 17, 1796, mentioning a recent visit from Tucker and a dance held the day of her departure. #9828-b
- Henrietta E. Randolph Papers 1796, 1 item.
- Henrietta E. Randolph Papers 1842-1849, 142 items.
  The papers consist chiefly of letters to Randolph from family in Clarke County, Virginia, and friends who attended school with her at the Rev. James McElroy's and Dr. Fisher's in Staunton, Virginia, and center on news of family and friends, illness and deaths, local events and religion. #10543
- John Randolph Letters 1814-1815, 2 items.
  In a widely circulated and copied letter, 1814 October 31, Randolph writes to Ann Cary (Randolph) Morris accusing her of the deaths of her child and her lover, John Randolph's brother. In the 1815 January 16 letter she refutes his charges. #10652
- Sarah Nicholas Randolph Photograph n.d., 1 item.
  Great-granddaughter of Thomas Jefferson. #10318
- Randolph Family Papers ca. 1760-1930, ca. 6000 items.
  Personal correspondence and business papers of the Randolph, Page, and Taylor families (descendants of Thomas Jefferson) of Albemarle County, Virginia, including many of the papers of Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Included is a letter of January 11, 1827, from a P. Leubal to [Thomas Jefferson Randolph] mentioning that the slave he recently bought from him [Randolph] named Jeanette had been severely burned by the overseer and thrown into a fire twice and that he could not return her because she feared for her life but that he believed her value is much less than the sale price. #8937, etc.
- Recollections of Piedmont ca. 1940, 1 item.
  A typescript copy of Jane Maury Maverick's remembrances of "Piedmont," the Albemarle County home of the Maurys. #2129
- Recipe Book ca. 1823-1890, 6 items.
  Includes recipe book, 1860s-1890s, inscribed January 20, 1868, kept by Jennie Taylor. #3518
- Recipe Book 1826, 1 item.
  Recipe book, 1826, from Charleston, [West] Virginia. #2025
- Reid Papers 1790-1910, 2500 items.
  Miscellaneous papers, primarily business in nature, relating to several Virginia families. Papers pertaining to women include the business papers of Elizabeth Spragins (d. 1842) of Halifax County, Virginia, and Mrs. Ann Thompson of Lynchburg, Virginia, both concerning tobacco sales. #550
- Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy Manuscript pre-1888, 1 item.
  An autograph one-page manuscript entitled A Sonnet. #1612
- Ameilie Rives Troubetzkoy 1927, 1 item.
  Letter, April 26, 1927, to Miss Scott in which she lists her least favorites of her own writings. #1586
- Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy 1887, 1920s-1930s, 1 item.
  One bound volume, Les Princes Troubetzkoy, Paris, 1888; and letters, including one to Mr. Henri S. Rorer, April 30, 1927, discussing her concept of history and literature. #214, -a, -b, -c
- Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy 1905, 1 item.
  Autograph manuscript of Augustine the Man. #2202
- Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy Papers 1853-1940, 10 Hollinger boxes.
  The manuscripts and correspondence of Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy and her second husband, Prince Pierre Troubetzkoy. Correspondents include Alice Kauser, Raphael Link and William Faversham. The collection consists primarily of manuscripts for different articles and books written by the Troubetzkoys. #2495, -a
- Margaret Rives 1832-1834, 1 item.
  Commonplace book of Margaret Rives including obituaries of the Rives family. #2313-a
- William Cabell Rives Papers 1861-1865, 61 items.
  Correspondence of the Rives family during the Civil War. Of interest are the touching letters of Mrs. Rives to her son, Afred Landon Rives, and his wife Sadie. #38-348
- Rives Family Papers 1791-1908, ca. 4000 items.
  Papers of the Rives Family of Castle Hill, Albemarle County, Virginia. Primarily of William Cabell Rives, Sr., Minister to France, U.S. Senator and Representative; papers of William C. Rives, Jr., covering farming operations at Castle Hill; papers of Alfred Landon Rives, railroad, mining canal and harbor engineer in the United States, Mexico, and Panama. Collection includes correspondence of William Cabell Rives, Sr. and his wife, Judith Page Walker Rives with their children Ella, Amelie, Francis, and William Cabell, Jr. The autobiography, last will and testament of Judith Walker Rives, as well as her poems, short stories, essays and translations from French are included. Other items of interest are the wills of Sadie Rives and Ella Rives, and correspondence and calling cards of the Rives women during stays in Paris. #2313
- Rives Family Papers 1822-1945, 500 items.
  Additional papers of the William Cabell Rives family of Castle Hill, Albemarle County, Virginia. The collection contains an album of verses by Cornelia Van Rensselaer to Judith Rives, as well as Judith Rives autobiography. Also included are Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy's childhood diary, journal, scrapbook, marriage book, and horoscopes. #2532.
- Rives Family Letters 1832-1882, 130 items.
  Letters by this Albemarle County, Virginia, family living at "Castle Hill," Cobham. Correspondents include Judith Page Walker Rives, Amelie Louise Rives Sigourney, and Ella Rives. #10596-c
- Bertha Gray Robinson Papers 1879-1941, 300 items.
  Editor and publisher of the Orange Observer, papers of Robinson include correspondence re the paper, 1880-1936, and subscription accounts, addresses, and lists. #1222.
- Mrs. Ellen Rogers 1843, 2 items.
  Two letters, March 5 and 20, 1843, from Ellen Rogers to her husband General Asa Rogers describing social life in Middleburg, Virginia. #2934
- Rorer Family Papers ca. 1770-1935, ca. 500 items.
  Business, legal, and personal papers of this family of Pittsylvania County, Virginia. A diary entry for February 24, 1848, mentions that a slave named Margaret murdered a white female baby of the family of John Jones and Angeline Rorer in Wentworth, North Carolina. Microfilm 1385; (#7901)
- Thomas Lafayette Rosser Papers 1860, ca. 1500 items.
  The papers of Thomas L. Rosser, Confederate Brigadier General, and chief engineer of the Northern Pacific Railroad. The papers fall into four distinct sets. The first collection (1171, -a, -b), 1860-1950, contains material regarding his wife Elizabeth (Betty) Winston Rosser, whom Rosser met and married during the Civil War, including correspondence (1875-1917), poetry, and a scrapbook she kept during the Civil War. Also included in the collection is the correspondence of the Rossers' granddaughter, Barbara Rosser. The second collection (1171-c), 1764 (1834-1910) 1969, concerns both the Gordon and Rosser families. The pre-Civil War correspondence between the Gordon sisters is not extensive, but provides a view of nineteenth century domestic life, as well as home manufacturing activities. Also included in this set of papers are more letters between Elizabeth (Betty) Winston Rosser and her husband. Topics include discussions of their upcoming wedding (April and May 1863), and denials of being involved and perhaps having been married to another woman (mid-summer 1863), and his promises that he will give up drinking. Also of interest is a letter from Elizabeth Custer to Mrs. Rosser regarding her involvement in a girls' club in New York City, Barbara Winston's will (1764), and some correspondence of Barbara Rosser. The third set of papers (1171, -d, -e, -f), 1858-1918, includes family correspondence. The last set of papers (1171-g, -h, -j), 1774 (1856-1899) 1980, contains Elizabeth Winston Rosser correspondence, 1862-1916, n.d.; Thomas L. Rosser, Jr. and his wife, Harriet Gordon Rosser correspondence, 1875-1951, n.d.; Barbara Rosser correspondence, 1906-1983, n.d.; financial and legal papers, 1865-1890; diaries of Elizabeth (Betty) Winston Rosser, 1866 April 28-May 16, 1872, 1913-1914; diary and letter book of Barbara Rosser, 1913-1915, 1916, 1865: a recipe book (ante 1860); and a poetry album of Harriet Hirtland or Kirkland, 1841-1842, 1844, 1877. #1171, -a-j
- Anne Newport Royall Letter 1826, 1 item.
  Letter, June 17, 1826, from Anne Newport Royall (1769-1854), Boston, Massachusetts, to Charles Ingersoll, New Haven, Connecticut, re Sketches of history, life, and manners, in the United States. #3559
- Rucker Family Papers 1890-1910, ca. 1000 items.
  Papers and photographs of William and Lulie Rucker of Washington, D.C., consisting primarily of letters to Mrs. Rucker. #1565
- Benjamin Franklin Dewees Runk Letters 1968, 2 items.
  In a letter, William L. Montague writes to Richard B. Gwathmey, Jr., editor of the Cavalier Daily, offering his views on the subject of co-education at the University of Virginia. #6852-j
- Mrs. Anna M. Rush Account Book 1913-1921, 1 item.
  Farm account book of Mrs. Rush, near Raphine, northern Rockbridge County, Virginia, with other loose manuscript material. #431.
- Sabine Hall/Landon Carter Papers 1659-1871, ca. 1000 items.
  Papers of Landon Carter of the Tidewater area of Virginia and the son of Robert "King" Carter. Collection is strong in 18th century material. However, most of the correspondence generated by women is nineteenth century. There are several colorful letters concerning women from the 18th century. Highlights are letters from Charles Carter to Landon Carter: April 26, 1758, writes that he found a woman 24 years old whom he planned to marry to take the place of his deceased wife; January 4, 1763, surprised that L. C.'s daughter Marie is to marry Robert Beverly, doubts his qualities and reports he frequently needs money and nearly killed a man in a duel; 1763, announces that his daughter, Judith, "by her own unalterable determination married Tuesday last." Rev. Isaac W. Giberne to Landon Carter, January 6, 1768, apologizes for his wife's bad manners for not accepting an invitation to Sabine Hall; Rev. Isaac Giberne writes of his wife's elopement and "who I am credibly informed, keeps company very night with some strolling players." Ralph Wormeley Carter to Landon Carter, May 10, 1774, reports that William Jackson, overseer at "Rippon" had pursued a wench who had failed his instructions," upon which he turned up her clothes and whipped her breach; I checked him for his mode of correction and made the matter up between them." Rev. Isaac W. Giberne to Landon Carter, attempts to have Carter repent his sworn enmity for Reuben Beale who had eloped with his daughter, Judith. The marriage proved to be a very happy one, but Carter never forgave the young man for his actions. (1959).
  Also of interest is a 50-page volume, ca. 1827-1914, containing Elizabeth Tayloe's poems and an inventory of household articles taken January 1838, and similar inventory dated 1914. (1959-a) #1959 and 1959-a
- Daniel Scanland 1849-1874, 30 items.
  Letters to Daniel Scanland of Middleburg, Loudoun County, Virginia, from members of his family in Walnut Dale, Pike County, Missouri concerning departures of California wagon trains, northern raids, and the hardships of non-combatants in the Civil War and life in general. Most of the letters are from his cousin Nancy Scanland written during 1851, recounting her life and activities. Nancy, a bit of a flirt, confides many of her feelings to her cousin Daniel and many of them concern romance. Highlights include a letter from Daniel's cousin, S. H. [Barnard] to Daniel dated September 18, 1852, concerning all the pretty unmarried girls to choose from in Missouri; November 23, 1851, Nancy writes Daniel to tell of her upcoming marriage and she laments the fact she will be separated from her family. From this letter and many others, one gets the idea that courtship was swift and sure on the frontier. There is only one letter to Daniel after her marriage to a Mr. Charles Benning. #2462.
- Mrs. Frederick W. Scott Papers 1951-1952, 2 items.
  Papers of the University of Virginia Hospital Circle, a volunteer hospital auxiliary society, contains a copy of the 1952 President's report and a 1951-1952 annual meeting report of the Circle; and a carbon copy of President's report filed in bound volume of Circle minutes #983-f
- Shackelford Family Papers ca. 1714 (1850-1990), ca. 9,000 items.
  Correspondence, financial and legal papers, genealogical material, printed material, photographs, bound volumes pertaining to the Shackelford family of "Willow Grove," Orange, Virginia. The papers relate to the family of Virginius Randolph Shackelford (1885-1959), his wife, Peachy Gascoigne Lyne (1887-1976), and their sons, Lyne Moncure (1914- ), Virginius Randolph (1916- ), and George Green (1920- ). #3525
- Shackelford Family Papers ca. 1914-1926, ca. 2,000 items.
  Correspondence and printed articles of the correspondence of Virginius Randolph Shackelford and Judge George S. Shackelford of Orange, Virginia, concerning Virginia politics and legislation, normal schools, highways, the University of Virginia, Woodberry Forest, the Monticello Association, and business and legal matters. Peachy Gascoigne (Lyne) Shackelford is a correspondent. #3525-a
- Shackelford Family Papers 1784, 1 item.
  Letter from Mann Page written to Colonel Oliver Towles, Spotsylvania, Virginia on August 4, 1784, the letter concerns a slave, George, who had applied for his freedom on the grounds that he was descended from a free Indian woman. #3525-s
- Shackelford Family Papers 1784, 1 item.
  The bulk of the collection consists of World War II correspondence between the Shackelford parents Virginius Randolph Shackelford and Peachy Gascoigne (Lyne) Shackelford and their sons from Woodberry Forest, Orange County, Virginia, and the University of Virginia. There is correspondence and related material re Virginius' public service as board member of the State Normal School for Women, East Radford, Virginia, the State Board of Education, the Virginia University Board of Visitors, and president of the Virginia State Bar Association. #3525 -ac, -ad, -ae
- Shackelford Family Papers 1950-1965, 10 items.
  Letters to Peachy Gascoigne (Lyne) Shackelford from family and friends writing thank-yous and invitations, renewing old acquaintances, and sending news of their families. Women correspondents are Virginia (Lyne) Chambers, Mary Pemberton Cox, Mary C. Gibbons, Peggy Moncure, Dorothy Walker, and Marguerite Lyne (Payne) Wornall. #3525-ai
- Shackelford Family Papers 1890-1977, ca. 800 items.
  Family correspondence, 1920-1977, chiefly among George Green Shackelford, Peachy Gascoigne (Lyne) Shakelford, Virginius Randolph Shackelford, Lyne, Moncure Shackelford, and Virginius Randolph Shackelford, Jr. Discuss local and family news, college days at the University of Virginia and Columbia, Navy duty, teaching at Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Blacksburg, Virginia, and sympathy at the death of Shackelford, Sr. #3525-aj, -ak
- Shackelford Family Papers 1937-1963, ca. 200 items.
  Correspondence of George Green Shackelford and his mother, Peachy Gascoigne (Lyne) Shackelford of "Willow Grove," Orange County, Virginia. Mrs. Shackelford writes news of family and friends in Orange County, and Shackelford writes about his University of Virginia schooldays and teaching positions, particularly as history professor at Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Blacksburg, Virginia. Photographs of Shackelford and his mother are included. #3525-al
- Shackelford Family Papers 1940, 1 item.
  Letter, September 26, 1940, from Josephine Maynard to Virginius Randolph and Peachy Gascoigne (Lyne) Shackelford, from Liverpool, England, during wartime, describing life at that time. Maynard furnished a very vivid description of German air raids over Great Britain and mentions several other aspects of life during wartime such as the morale of the British during the "blitz raids," the collapse of France, American air aid relief, difficulty of communication with other parts of Great Britain, rationing "tough drunks," living in public air raid shelters, and the Germany-Italy-Japan Axis Alliance. 3525-am
- Shackelford Family Papers ca. 1850 (1909-1990), ca. 2,500 items.
  Chiefly correspondence between George Shackelford and his brothers Lyne Moncure Shackelford and Virginius Randolph Shackelford, his wife Grace Howard (McConnell) Shackelford, his father Virginius Randolph Shackelford, and several nieces and nephews. Topics include Lyne and Shackelford family genealogy, family financial and business matters, family property including "Willow Grove," the estate of Peachy Gascoigne (Lyne) Shackelford, the Monticello Association, the West Lawn Marching and Chowder Society, and the 1941 football team and its five year reunion. Included is a photograph album, ca. 1850, belonging to Mrs. Belle Kirk Shackelford. 3525-as, -at
- Shepherd Family (1836-1878) 1948, 118 items.
  Legal and business papers of William Stephen Shepherd and Lucy D. Shepherd of Fluvanna County, Virginia. The latter day items are the records of Susie V. Shepherd. #3041
- Lydia Sigourney Letter 1840, 1 item.
  Letter, June 17, 1840, Lydia H. Sigourney to Miss Mary Allen, happy to grant Miss Allen's request. #38-342
- Sively Family Papers 1877-1899, 125 items.
  Business and family letters of George L. and Mary C. Sively of Mountain Grove, Bath County, Virginia. Included are letters from Sallie (Sively) Erwin while a student at Hollins Institute and after her marriage to Dr. James E. Erwin and their migration west to Kansas. Correspondence between Mary Sively and her sister, Elizabeth Skeen of Franklin County, Virginia, concerning their interest in the rental or sale of the "homeplace" and farm. The sisters had trouble with delinquent renters, trespassers, and timber cutters. #1277
- Jane Chapman Slaughter Papers 1828-1951, 651 items.
  Miscellaneous collection of papers brought together by Jane Chapman Slaughter. Included is Ms. Slaughter's correspondence concerning family history, sketchbooks of pencil, drawings, 1872-1983, by her, as well as some of her academic papers and her 1923 M. A. thesis, "Velasquez and His Art." #38-709
- Slave Bill of Sale 1845, 1 item.
  Bill of Sale, January 25, 1845, to Joseph Dinwiddie for the sale of a female slave, Sarah, to William Dinwiddie for $700. #3194-h
- Margaret Bell Dunnington Sloan Letter 1895, 1 item.
  A letter, October 28, 1895, from this Charlottesville, Virginia resident and University of Virginia professor's daughter, to her sister, Sadie Dunnington, Hollins Institute, about the Rotunda fire, and her father's efforts to save the building. #10647
- Susan Dabney Smedes 1908-1911, 13 items.
  Letters and diary of Susan Dabney Smedes, author of A Southern Planter. The diary and letters pertain to her visits to Great Britain. Typescripts and originals. #38-373
- Susan Dabney Smedes 1886-1907, 21 items.
  Letters to Susan Dabney Smedes from Augustus Hare, Lord Northington, Sir Henry Ponsonby, C. M. Yonge, William E. Gladstone, John Murray, J. A. Froude, Charles Dudley Warner, Jeanie D. Hogg, John Murray, and Andrew Lang. #2655.
- Smiley Family Papers 1827-1934, 390 items.
  Correspondence, financial and legal papers of the Smiley family of Moffat's Creek, Augusta County, Virginia. Collections include a 1772 letter from John Lancaster, Pennsylvania to his wife, correspondence of Letitia Smiley with related papers while attending Augusta Female Seminary, 1864-1867, and Mary A. Smiley's notebook. #1807-a
- Mary Kelly Watson Smith Papers 1814-1884, 90 items.
  Chiefly letters from Mary Kelly Watson Smith to her sister, Hortense Hay Watson. The majority of the correspondence was written in the decade after 1859, when Mary moved from Charlottesville with her husband, Jacob Henry Smith, to Greensboro, North Carolina. The letters contain details of life during and after the Civil War. Some of these letters have been published in the Love That Never Failed, printed by the Michie Company in 1928. #Microfilm M-38; 1624
- Edward Nelson and Susan Massie (Snead) Smith Papers 1927-1984, 15 items.
  Correspondence of Edward Smith and his wife, Susan Massie (Snead) Smith. There are two combinations diaries and commonplace books, 1927-1934, kept by Edward with additional two comments made years later by Susan about the significance of the events that occurred on those dates to her husband and herself. Also included are several letters to Susan praising her as a teacher, two letters to Edward thanking him for his assistance, notes re Susan's educational experiences, clippings of sentimental value to the Smiths, and a photograph inscribed to Susan from [Edward]. #10544-b
- Elizabeth Oakes Smith Papers 1823-1894, 4,000 items.